Uh my name is Sergey. I'm a manager in
the CI team like continuous kernel
integration. Uh we build CI for kernel.
And today I'm going to tell you about
how to do uh how we do one-on-one
meetings or at least how I try to do it.
I see
many people here. So, uh basically uh
like
I believe you know how to do one-on-one
meetings and you had once right in
general but uh maybe my experience that
I will share like will be helpful for
you. So uh let's go for it. Uh the first
question that appears here like
basically do we need one-on- ones in
general like at companies like I know
some companies uh don't have like
one-on-one meetings like who thinks that
one-on- ones we should have like one
ones
there are quite quite number of people
it's nice and uh the correct answer of
course yes like we need it uh why it's
so like uh there was a um
some statistic information about like
companies who like uh which like uh have
one-on-one meetings and companies uh uh
which like don't have like one-on-one
meetings. So in in case of like if
company has like one-on-one meetings uh
there like uh basically like happiness
of like employers like higher the like
progress and development also like
higher. So having one-on-one meetings
like I just tell you like regular
one-on-one meetings with like managers
with associates is like uh important
because you you have like uh like higher
results in the end I mean in the long
term uh way.
So uh why I decided to talk about like
one-on-one meetings like because once I
uh become a manager I did it in the
wrong way. I I basically I didn't know
how to do like one-on-one meetings like
we talk about like anything and nothing
and we tried to like uh shared some
ideas ways and so on but it wasn't
exactly like uh uh the like the right
way how how to do it. So uh most people
like not not most but many many managers
like uh do one one meetings and just
want to hear like uh status update. It's
not about it like at all like one-on-one
meetings shouldn't be like it's like not
equal to status update. So it's one like
uh big mistake. Second it's that you you
don't have like real connection with
your like uh guys your team. So
basically it just like I am a manager I
am in a higher position and you're like
uh engineer so just report to me and so
on. it it's not the right like so
one-on-one meeting should be on like
equal level like uh each one-on-one
meeting and in general there is a second
problem so uh third one it's about
skipping important topics so some
manager thinks okay this meeting is for
me like I want to get some information
from the person so I ask about status
update uh I'm trying to like solve my
own issues and don't hear like to to
guys don't listen to them and just uh
it's about like skipping main point here
that uh such people they uh they losing
their like ability to like to help
people or to just you know like improve
connections and development of people
and as I mentioned before like
one-on-one meetings meetings it's not
for managers I will tell you like later
about it but uh like mostly one-on-one
meetings is for like people and
associates. It's not like for managers.
Managers needs to like uh you know drive
and and lead meetings but not just being
like on the top of it and like hearing
about like uh what was done, what wasn't
done and why and so on. So what is like
one-on-one meeting? Uh one-on-one
meeting is basically a meeting between
uh manager and team member and uh there
are several topics that could be like
discussed like there like first it's
like motivation of the person like how
this person is motivated to do things
what they like to do what don't like to
do uh like how they feel doing some like
activities and so on for example I see
like people uh from my team like and I
know that they definitely don't like
doing UI part of like some stuff like I
I don't like max doing that. I tried to
find some somebody else who like really
likes to do it like there is one thing
uh also about the progress progress it's
not about status it's about how person
thinks uh like uh his pro progress is so
like for example you can ask question
like how do you feel like were you
productive like last week or not
productive like uh like how do you feel
and for example the reply was yeah I
feel like I was really productive
because I did like uh of like uh like
many things and like I'm also like what
like even more that I planned and I feel
like happy and healthy because I like
you know working without like
interruptions without like additional
meetings and so on.
So the third thing is like talk about
goal goals and personal growth like uh I
know some people that uh then don't like
to be promoted they like uh working in
the way they are doing and don't like
like moving forward. So uh it's not like
many it's like 10% or 5% of such people
like other guys they they like talking
about growth but uh sometimes they are
way too shy you know to discuss such
things. So as a manager like you need to
like uh start talking like first for
example like I see that you are like
have like great potential at I don't
know like uh as an engineer so let's
discuss your like further promotions and
step and so on. Yeah. And uh in that
case you can like set goals. Uh the same
is like career plans and development. So
it's basically uh what I mentioned like
uh right now. So just uh in this uh case
you're just discussing uh setting up the
goals discussing things and try to help
like person to reach those goals
uh about uh like schedule of the
meeting. So uh
once you become a manager in a team or
somebody becomes like a manager new
manager in the team. So you probably uh
set need to like uh like meet with your
team like talk to everybody and uh
establish like plan for your team.
Usually like managers set up like
meetings because they are like really
busy people you know like they don't
have time to do like anything and and so
on and so on. uh in my team I always ask
people like uh if like would you feel
comfortable if I like set meeting like
uh for example on Monday or on Tuesday
at at particular time usually I ask
person to set up like meeting like in
the way like uh he or she wants like uh
here is a thing that it should be like
regular meetings so it shouldn't be like
we have like one meeting and then like
after like one week another one and then
in one month like third meeting it
should be like regular like uh meetings
could be like weekly bi-weekly or
monthly like it's not connected to whole
team like having meetings like exactly
like for example let's say I have a CPI
team so we do like one-on-one meeting
monthly it doesn't work like that so
talk to each person like directly and
like ask like see like how this person
behaves like for example if they need
like more meetings like uh let's say in
uh in our team we have be weekly
meetings. Sometimes guys ask me to have
like additional one-on- ones like when
they need to solve something or share
something and so on. So uh those like uh
bly meetings it's like scheduled and
like basically official like I would say
and uh those meetings like uh like
mostly we have like uh regularly and
some meetings come up like uh like
weekly and more often for example with
some guys like uh I have meetings like
weekly sometimes like be weekly. So it
depends on the person of the team but
not team itself. Uh
also
uh
be sure that uh your guys interested in
those meetings because sometimes like uh
guys not really want to have like
meetings because don't don't have uh
anything to discuss let's say and and
some other reasons. So you should be
like uh you should also think about it
and do meetings in the way that people
like really uh feel comfortable at this
meetings and like uh in ideal case that
people like want to have like meetings
to discuss some things.
Yeah. Uh so about like uh having
meetings like and stages of the
meetings. So usually like uh it has like
three four steps stages there like uh
first stage is just before the meeting.
What you like doing before the meeting?
I know some managers who is like really
experienced and they don't need to
prepare for meetings. I usually like
prepare for meetings because I want to
to know like exactly like what what we
talked about last time what uh what was
done like for example some promises uh
and so on some activities and what we
going to do like next. So it's like
really when you have for example like uh
four people in the team it's easier to
remember everything but if you have like
10 person in the team uh you might lose
like so restart is when you just
remember everything what you discussed
what you promised and just uh to have
like next uh steps. So uh the start uh f
face phase of the
uh it's like set the tone. So for
example at this meeting you want to talk
about like uh promotion or maybe next
time you want to talk about gapes uh
like next up you want to like coach
person because like uh like you was
asked to do that and uh that's why like
you can like discuss those steps and uh
like uh behave in that way. uh central
phrase it's really important because uh
like uh despite of talking about nothing
it's the main part that you can when you
can like uh understand person like put
some goals discuss important things and
so on and uh the last one is end
positively so you like basically I don't
suggest ending meetings in the way that
uh okay so you have you missed deadline
you have some gapes please work on it
like it doesn't work. It shouldn't work
like that. So basically like uh try to
appreciate like help like try to find
something that person like really your
passion working on and what like he or
she really done like during like between
the meetings
some questions you might help you like
uh uh with meetings like it's like
really easy like and uh like but uh I
would like to just like talk about this
a bit. So, uh you might ask like what
issues do you have some obstacles when
when you stuck like what do you like to
talk about? So just uh try to ask like
open questions, try to like uh show that
you really like uh want to solve those
issues, not just talking like about like
you you know like just because we have
those questions we need to ask exactly
those questions at each meeting and
that's like our schedule like our agenda
for the meeting and that's it. So note
in the in it's work it doesn't work in
that way. So the main part should be
like like this. So you you need to get
like uh person like uh get this person
that he or she just uh you know be open
with you that you know the information
and know like how to help this person.
So uh you can ask about like priorities
of this person feels what was what went
well what went not really well because
like for example at any particular
situation that happened like during like
uh during like last week let's say uh
it's really like uh people think
differently and people feel like
different for like uh about like uh
changes for example for example like if
we had some uh new like uh let's say new
guy in the team. So some people might
feel like well about it, some people
might not feel like well and maybe some
people don't like don't know like what
what what to like talk about with this
person, how to like dealing with it, how
to start communicating. So that's why
you need to lead like those meetings and
ask uh like such like as an example such
such questions. Yeah.
Uh also like I recommend in the uh like
end when you like for example talked
about uh your like goals that you set up
or like uh guys set up. So you can talk
about anything else. Maybe something is
like really like important and uh guys
want to discuss with you. So yeah don't
be don't be too shy and just try to ask
like people about this.
So uh as I talked about like status
update issue, it's not about like
one-on-one meetings. It's definitely not
about like status update. It it's not
exactly for managers. So one-on-one
meetings like in ideal case should be
set up by uh associates like uh your
guys and uh like and do like in in the
way like they set it up and don't
discuss like uh status update. for
example to get some status update you
have like way more like different
variants where you can get it you can go
to Jira for example and check for like
uh like tasks like what was closed like
you can go I don't know GitLab GitHub
you can ask other people like and and so
on so don't spend this time like at
meetings if you want like directly talk
to this person like about status update
just call this meeting like status
update and everybody will be afraid of
it like and nobody wants to go into it
Yeah. So it's the same uh instead of
like asking like highlights you can ask
like about like instead of asking about
status update you can ask about
highlights from during last week. It's
like not the same like a status update.
For example status update uh could be
like uh uh speech about like let's say
oh I did this task nothing nothing
blocks me and I'm going to do this task
and so on. But when you ask about
highlights uh like for example guys
usually ask how how they did it like
what like challenges they face up and
you can as a manager just uh see how
like this person like dealing with
issues and maybe like next time you will
like open some potentials maybe work
with people like more or more technical
way. So it depends on like how person
like behaves. So and also you can
discuss like priorities and so on. So
please don't uh discuss tus updates uh
at the meetings.
Sometimes as a manager you can ask about
feedback.
So I mention here sometimes because uh
you you can do it like every meeting but
it would be like not uh like really good
because it's like uh it spends some time
and you don't want to spend some
person's time when you talk about uh
like their activities and their
development about like your feedback.
But as a manager you like uh and if you
want to grow like you can uh ask really
like about feedback sometimes like for
example as a question like uh what I
like how do you feel like I'm a good
manager what should I do like more
should do less or maybe should I stop
doing something or maybe should I
continue like or just start doing
something it it's like completely fine
like
So also you can ask about uh feedback.
Yeah. Uh so at the meetings you like uh
the the main like uh I would say skill
that you need to have is like listen to
person. Don't interrupt. Don't just you
know like break don't like change the
topic of discussion. You just uh need to
listen to understand then just you know
to respond. Don't like think that okay
now this person is talking and I need to
respond something to him. No no no just
understand is like try to understand
sometimes like for example as I'm not
technical person anymore uh I don't
understand like something that they are
talking like to me about like AI or some
like stuff like technical details. So if
I don't want to look stupid, I just tell
tell this guy, okay, I don't want to
look stupid, but please could you
describe a bit more or maybe on a higher
level because I don't understand what do
you mean like and and so on. So uh also
some like questions that might help you
as a manager like to like dealing with
people to understand more. Don't be
afraid like admit that you don't
understand something because uh in some
ways there are some specific like topics
that like they working for uh they've
been working for like maybe I don't know
months and only they know like about it
but you're not aware of it. So try to
get it on a higher level and uh try to
respond like based on this information.
Yeah. at the meetings uh
you need to ask if people like basically
have everything like what they need to
finish like tasks. So sometimes for
example uh like lately in in my team
like guys started working at AI and uh
obviously they don't have resources for
training models like so everybody like
was involved in this pro like who wanted
they were involved in this process and
in the end oh we don't have resources.
So try to figure this out and try to
discuss with guys if they need anything.
Maybe they need some information. Maybe
for example uh some company changes you
know and they don't really understand
it. So try to like explain and ask if
like there are like uh some things that
uh like you want to discuss or like want
to need more information about it. Uh
also try to ask people like open
questions like not just close like are
you feel well like yeah so and and so on
like yeah yeah yeah would you work on
this? Of course like like try to change
some like for open questions like if
like for example would you like working
on it? How do you feel about like
working on it? Like it would be fine for
you like and so on and so on. Uh also
try to like seek for communication gaps.
of if you like sometimes like you might
feel that you stuck or like this person
you know this like awkward silence.
Yeah. So try to just switch to another
like topic and discuss like maybe
something else.
Yeah. Uh meetings it's about balance. Uh
it's about like practical needs and
personal needs. uh like on the left side
you see this like words like plan,
develop, destination, decision, reach,
problems and so on. On the other hand uh
we have like feelings like it's like
personal needs. So you cannot like you
basically you can't tell person to do
something uh when they don't want to do
something they they will do and then
after some period of time they just like
left and because of like uh you don't
use this like uh right column always ask
how how they feel like doing it if they
feel okay if they feel fine like uh like
feel respected valuable and so on. Uh
sometimes people uh like don't feel
valuable because like they don't get
like real feedback like on time because
they they finish like way more things
and don't don't get any feedback like
about it. So you can balance between all
this like two parts.
Okay. Uh about
uh we talked about managers uh behavior
how how manager leadings. Now talk about
like uh what association part like
basically I'm a manager but I have also
like my manager and uh uh as a like
associate for for my manager. So how
should I behave at this meetings? So you
basically as you like as associate is
important like uh for like uh setting up
meetings for like uh discussing things
like it's meeting not for managers so
you probably should be active at this
meeting at this role uh also it would be
great if you know what you need I mean
what do you need to discuss like you
have several topics like before the
meeting you can share with your manager
for example it's like at this meeting I
want to discuss ask like this this and
that and okay no problem at all you can
also tell about it like uh at the
meeting uh also uh you you can ask uh
for help not just just I I don't
understand anything just I need some
help uh ask exactly what you want to
help uh always I I I think like you can
always ask for feedback it's completely
fine how how I'm doing what exactly like
uh what I what needs to be done better
what what I need to do like uh better
and so on. So uh sometimes people like
work hard and they even don't understand
like how valuable they are because
managers don't provide like and they
don't know whether it's like normal
speed or they need to increase the speed
and like yeah so and also like receive
feedback ask your manager like provide
feedback to your manager if you need to
change something or you see like the
situation need be changed or you think
manager like doesn't behave in the like
direction that you thought about. So
also al also like provide feedback
cancelling one-on- ones uh uh all any
guy in my team can cancel oneonone just
without like anything told me just I I
want to cancel like I cannot like you
know attend to this meeting so uh you
should reschedule it like immediately
don't just you know forget about it oh
cancel like uh one meeting less I am
fine so like good yeah no no you need to
rescule it then you need to discuss what
you want it to it should be regular. If
you like loses regularity it might go
like not well.
So uh after the meetings you need to
think about what you like promise to do
like how you going to do it and how you
like make this things happen. So like
the things that can break uh your trust
is just broken commit commitments and uh
like yeah basically that's that's the
main point. So if you promise to do
something or you agreed on something
like I mean as a manager so you need to
uh be committed to like finish it on
time. Yeah. And uh like uh the same is
for associate if you agreed on something
so please like behave in the same way.
Yeah. So uh wrapping up our presentation
uh one-on-one meetings is meetings like
between uh between managers and uh guys
in your team. At those meetings like you
should listen like listen to understand
not to ask people and try as much as
possible like help like associates like
with uh their needs. like it could could
be like some uh current task maybe some
development process setting up goals and
so on. Thank you.
[Applause]
Any questions?
What is the right question to
what is the right question to get
feedback? If if I ask like how am I
doing? Am I doing good and I don't get
anything apart like a thumbs up? Yeah.
About feedback. So you can ask like uh
if you're not sure you can ask uh can I
get feedback from you or may I provide
feedback to you like you the first
question and then like if you like for
example ask about feedback like may may
I get feedback from you like and then
like just ask what you want like for
example like what I'm doing well like is
my speed is okay like like is I like
what I am doing is valuable like what do
you think should I increase like my
speed and should I be like slower like
is it fine or not fine like just be
honest like it's it's the main like
idea. So don't be shy like managers also
like would like to provide feedback to
people. So if you like do this first
step so it would be like uh the way then
you can like speak about it more
you can like set up topic like about
like my current activities and my like
workload and what I'm working on like
let's discuss and provide feedback.
Yeah.
So, um what is one thing that you
changed in your approach to one-on-one
meetings that perhaps you've um like
learned over your um learned through
your experience and it had a positive
impact in the end like one thing in your
one-on-one approach. So, so like uh now
I I don't like uh discuss u start status
at one-on-one meetings is like it's one
thing main thing that I change. Second,
I told uh all the guys that meetings for
them like not for me like they can uh
set up, they can cancel it, but it
should be regularly like it doesn't
matter what uh the like uh uh like time
for meetings it's also like on them
because maybe they don't feel like
having meetings on Monday in the morning
somebody like yeah that's the thing and
uh like also like now now I'm trying to
change it goes like hard but I I'm
trying like working on it. It's just uh
having some notes like that shared with
every like shared with this person. Uh
because right now I have like only uh
you know notes on my laptop that I just
wrote writing down and uh like like it's
hard you know like uh make some notes
like always like each meetings to
discuss but yeah I believe it will
change also like in the positive way.
Uh you also mentioned uh regarding uh
meeting cadence that it's different for
different team members and that
sometimes they request an additional
meeting. Does the request always come
from their side or is it some sometimes
that um like you see that the person
would benefit from another meeting and
you're the one that increases the
cadence. Yeah. So, so in in my case it's
usually they uh those request comes from
their side like from my side it's very
rary when I like want to talk like them
uh and usually guys to want to discuss
like some things that uh they not feel
like well about it for example like
recently we changed like our ways for um
ways of like development and we we like
moved from uh from KBAN let's say to
scrum and like some guys worries about
it and they just wanted to ask like why
we doing it, what benefits it will bring
and so on. So and that time I had like
way more meetings that's just normal in
normal life. Yeah.
Okay. One question to the taking notes.
Um
how how do you make these notes? Um do
you make it after the meeting or do you
take it while you're talking to the
persons or like basically it doesn't
matter if you feel comfortable doing it
like during meeting for example you have
1 hour you can like discuss things and
you can do it like during meetings notes
uh but if you feel like okay with this
you you can do it like after the meeting
uh the the main thing is that like like
as as I like it should be measurable for
example you you like uh you ask manager
you tell manager okay I want to be
promoted like I feel like I I'm just
doing completely fine and I want to be
promoted okay uh like the manager tells
you okay so uh let's work on your
visibility and you make notes work on my
visibility what it means like work on
visibility what should I do like is it
it's not measurable so for example you
can discuss okay you have one
presentation at at defcon you can have
like two like send five emails per month
to somebody and you basically maybe have
some I I don't know like some mentee for
example or just somebody who you can
work with so like collaborate start
collaborating with another team so it's
measurable things so everything that you
promised or you were promised to do it
should be like written and shared
between you both and then uh it should
be like measurable to just see where you
uh right now.
Okay. Um and second question, uh what is
the time you save for these meetings?
How long do you normally make these
meetings? You mean each meeting
individually in like do you always make
an hour or just 50 minutes or No, no. We
usually we have like 30 minutes but it
also depends on on on the p on the
person and on topic we discussed. So
basically we have like regular meeting
is like 30 minutes uh every two like
every other week and when we want like
have more we can have more and if for
example like guys want to cancel it I
don't know some vacation period or some
like uh and so on. So yeah, fine. But
some sometimes we we go with like for 1
hour like yeah up to 1 hour. Like I
don't recommend uh doing it like more
than one hour because like people get
tired like
any other questions.
One more question.
I would like to ask you how you would
handle a not so good news. Let's say
someone did something, there was a
change, something doesn't went so good.
Even if the whole team was sitting some
over times to correct it, but
bad news or to say so. Yeah. Yeah.
Not so nice things that can happen
happened. How you communicate that with
a personally
because some people especially don't
like bad news. Yeah, nobody likes bad
news. I tell you more. So I I also like
it's the hardest things like for me to
provide like bad news. But I I'm trying
to be honest. I even if bad news happens
like I'm try to like find ways where we
can like solve this issue like what
happened or just at least find some
compromise at it. So I don't like try
that okay there is bad news and we going
to work in that way right now but need
to discuss like need to like understand
person's feelings like and so on and
just be honest just tell okay it's like
not only for you like good news for
example for everybody so let's go
together and work so yeah just be being
honest
thank
[Applause]